<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % myentities SYSTEM "../bugle.ent" >
%myentities;
]>
<refentry id="gldb-gui.1">
    <refentryinfo>
        <date>October 2007</date>
        <productname>BUGLE</productname>
    </refentryinfo>
    <refmeta>
        <refentrytitle>gldb-gui</refentrytitle>
        <manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
    </refmeta>

    <refnamediv>
        <refname>gldb-gui</refname>
        <refpurpose>graphical OpenGL debugger</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>

    <refsynopsisdiv>
        <cmdsynopsis>
            <command>gldb-gui</command>
            <arg choice="plain"><replaceable>your-program</replaceable></arg>
            <arg rep="repeat"><replaceable>argument</replaceable></arg>
        </cmdsynopsis>
    </refsynopsisdiv>

    <refsect1 id="gldb-gui-MAN-start">
        <title>Getting started</title>
        <para>The command above will start <command>gldb-gui</command>, but
            will not start your program. To do that, use 
            <menuchoice>
                <guimenu>Run</guimenu>
                <guimenuitem>Run</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>. Your program will automatically stop if it
            generates an OpenGL error. You can also stop it manually by
            selecting
            <menuchoice>
                <shortcut>
                    <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Break</keycap></keycombo>
                </shortcut>
                <guimenu>Run</guimenu>
                <guimenuitem>Stop</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>. See <xref linkend="gldb-gui-MAN-breakpoints"/> for
            information on stopping your program when it calls particular
            OpenGL functions. You can continue your program with
            <menuchoice>
                <shortcut>
                    <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>F9</keycap></keycombo>
                </shortcut>
                <guimenu>Run</guimenu>
                <guimenuitem>Continue</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>,
            continue until the next OpenGL function call with
            <menuchoice>
                <shortcut>
                    <keycap>F8</keycap>
                </shortcut>
                <guimenu>Run</guimenu>
                <guimenuitem>Step</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>,
            or kill it with
            <menuchoice>
                <shortcut>
                    <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>F2</keycap></keycombo>
                </shortcut>
                <guimenu>Run</guimenu>
                <guimenuitem>Kill</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <tip>
            <para>
                Your program can only be stopped or killed when it calls an OpenGL
                function. If your program updates its display only when necessary,
                it may not stop immediately. You can often force it an update by
                placing another window over your program and then removing it
                again.
            </para>
        </tip>
        <para>
            The interface is separated into a number of tabs. You can browse
            them at any time, but the information will only be up-to-date when
            your program is stopped. When your program is running, the status
            bar will contain the text
            <computeroutput>Running</computeroutput>.
        </para>
    </refsect1>
    <refsect1 id="gldb-gui-MAN-state">
        <title>Examining OpenGL state</title>
        <para>
            The initial tab is the <guilabel>State</guilabel> tab. It shows
            all OpenGL state that is textual rather than an image. The state
            is organised roughly more or less according to the state tables in
            the <ulink
                url="http://www.opengl.org/registry/doc/glspec21.20061201.pdf">OpenGL
                specification.</ulink> OpenGL has an
            overwhelming amount of state, so some tools are provided to make
            it easier to find answers:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para>To find a specific state, press
                    <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>F</keycap></keycombo>.
                    This opens a text entry box where you can type in the name
                    of the state.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>To show only the states that
                    changed since the last time the program was stopped, check
                    the <guilabel>Show only modified</guilabel> checkbox.
                    These states are also shown in bold.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>To track only a small set of states, check the
                    checkboxes next to those states, then check the
                    <guilabel>Show only selected</guilabel>
                    checkbox.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>To save all the states to an XML file, click the
                    <guibutton>Save</guibutton> button.</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <refsect2 id="gldb-gui-MAN-state-texture">
            <title>Examining textures</title>
            <para>
                The <guilabel>Texture</guilabel> tab shows OpenGL textures.
                The <guilabel>Texture</guilabel> combobox allows a texture to
                be selected, with the currently bound texture of each type
                shown in bold. For cubemap textures, the
                <guilabel>Face</guilabel> combobox allows one of the sides to
                be examined in detail; the default is to show two views of the
                cube itself. For 3D textures, a slice may be selected with the
                <guilabel>Z</guilabel> combobox.
            </para>
            <para>The apparent size of the texture is controlled through the
                <guilabel>Zoom</guilabel> combobox. <guilabel>Fit</guilabel>
                makes the texture as large as possible while still fitting the
                window. The other settings set a ratio between texels and
                screen pixels. The toolbar also has buttons to 
                <guiicon>
                    <inlinemediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <objectinfo>
                                <corpauthor>GTK+</corpauthor>
                            </objectinfo>
                            <imagedata fileref="gtk-zoom-in.png"
                                format="PNG"/>
                        </imageobject>
                        <textobject><phrase></phrase></textobject>
                    </inlinemediaobject>
                </guiicon>
                zoom in,
                <guiicon>
                    <inlinemediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <objectinfo>
                                <corpauthor>GTK+</corpauthor>
                            </objectinfo>
                            <imagedata fileref="gtk-zoom-out.png"
                                format="PNG"/>
                        </imageobject>
                        <textobject><phrase></phrase></textobject>
                    </inlinemediaobject>
                </guiicon>
                zoom out, set a 
                <guiicon>
                    <inlinemediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <objectinfo>
                                <corpauthor>GTK+</corpauthor>
                            </objectinfo>
                            <imagedata fileref="gtk-zoom-100.png"
                                format="PNG"/>
                        </imageobject>
                        <textobject><phrase></phrase></textobject>
                    </inlinemediaobject>
                </guiicon>
                1:1 ratio, or
                <guiicon>
                    <inlinemediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <objectinfo>
                                <corpauthor>GTK+</corpauthor>
                            </objectinfo>
                            <imagedata fileref="gtk-zoom-fit.png"
                                format="PNG"/>
                        </imageobject>
                        <textobject><phrase></phrase></textobject>
                    </inlinemediaobject>
                </guiicon>
                fit to the window size.
            </para>
            <para>The appearance of the texture may be controlled with the
                <guilabel>Mag filter</guilabel> and <guilabel>Min
                    filter</guilabel> comboboxes. These settings correspond to
                the <symbol>GL_TEXTURE_MAG_FILTER</symbol> and
                <symbol>GL_TEXTURE_MIN_FILTER</symbol> in OpenGL. However,
                these settings are only used for displaying the texture, and
                do not affect your program. The <guilabel>Level</guilabel>
                combobox makes it possible to examine specific texture levels.
                The default (<guilabel>Auto</guilabel>) uses mipmapping as
                defined by <guilabel>Min filter</guilabel>.
            </para>
            <para>In some cases, there may not be enough contrast in the
                texture to see any details (this is particularly true of
                textures that encode non-graphical information, such as lookup
                tables). Checking <guilabel>Remap range</guilabel> will scale
                the colour range up (or down) to cover the whole [0, 1] range.
                To perform more detailed image analysis, use the
                <guiicon>
                    <inlinemediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <objectinfo>
                                <corpauthor>GTK+</corpauthor>
                            </objectinfo>
                            <imagedata fileref="gtk-copy.png"
                                format="PNG"/>
                        </imageobject>
                        <textobject><phrase>Copy</phrase></textobject>
                    </inlinemediaobject>
                </guiicon>
                button to
                copy the texture to the clipboard, and paste it into an
                external application such as the GIMP.
            </para>
            <note><para>The copy feature is only available when compiled with
                    GTK+ 2.6 or later.</para></note>
        </refsect2>
        <refsect2 id="gldb-gui-MAN-state-framebuffer">
            <title>Examining framebuffers</title>
            <para>Framebuffers may be viewed in much the same way as textures
                (see <xref linkend="gldb-gui-MAN-state-texture"/>). The
                <guilabel>Framebuffer</guilabel> may be set to either the
                current window-system framebuffer, or to a framebuffer
                created with <function>glCreateFramebufferEXT</function>.
                Pbuffers that are no the current drawable are not supported.
            </para>
            <para>Within a framebuffer, <guilabel>Buffer</guilabel> may be set
                to the front buffer, back buffer, depth buffer, stencil buffer
                or an auxiliary buffer, depending on which buffers actually
                exist.
            </para>
        </refsect2>
        <refsect2 id="gldb-gui-MAN-state-shaders">
            <title>Examining shaders</title>
            <para>
                The <guilabel>Shaders</guilabel> tab shows the source of
                low-level ARB shaders and high-level GLSL shaders.
                Vendor-specific shader extensions are not supported. The
                current shader of each type is shown in bold in the combobox.
            </para>
            <para>Further information about the shader may be found on the
                <guilabel>State</guilabel> tab.
            </para>
        </refsect2>
    </refsect1>
    <refsect1 id="gldb-gui-MAN-breakpoints">
        <title>Setting breakpoints</title>
        <para>The <guilabel>Breakpoints</guilabel> allows breakpoints to be
            set on specific OpenGL functions. Immediately before calling the
            function, your program will be stopped and the status bar will
            indicate which function caused the breakpoint.
        </para>
        <para>Click <guibutton>Add</guibutton> to set a new breakpoint, and
            enter the name of the function into the dialog box that appears.
            To remove a function from the list, click
            <guibutton>Remove</guibutton>. If you are likely to want to break
            on that function later, it is easier to deselect the
            <guilabel>Enabled</guilabel> checkbox for the function, and select
            it again later.
        </para>
        <tip><para>Keep in mind that a function may have multiple aliases (for
                example, <function>glBeginQuery</function> and
                <function>glBeginQueryARB</function>), and you need to select
                the right one.</para></tip>
        <para>By default, <command>gldb-gui</command> will stop when a
            function generates an OpenGL error. This can be disabled by
            deselecting <guilabel>Break on errors</guilabel>. Note that
            function breakpoints occur before the function is called, but
            errors occur afterwards, so <command>gldb-gui</command> may stop
            twice for the same function.
        </para>
    </refsect1>
    <refsect1 id="gldb-gui-MAN-gdb">
        <title>Interacting with gdb</title>
        <para>When your program is stopped, the <guilabel>Backtrace</guilabel>
            tab shows the current call stack of your program, as
            <command>gdb</command> would. The first few frames (usually those
            up to <function>run_filters</function>) will be internal to
            <application>bugle</application>.
        </para>
        <para>To further examine the state of your program, select
            <menuchoice>
                <guimenu>Run</guimenu>
                <guimenuitem>Attach GDB</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>. Provided that you have <command>xterm</command> and
            <command>gdb</command> installed, this will open a terminal window
            running <command>gdb</command>, already attached to your program.
            Once you have finished, you may either quit <command>gdb</command>
            and detach it from your program, or keep it open and
            <userinput>continue</userinput> in <command>gdb</command>.
        </para>
        <note><para>Your program needs to be running from the point of view of
                <command>gdb</command> for <command>gldb-gui</command> to
                function correctly.</para></note>
    </refsect1>

    <refsect1 id="gldb-gui-MAN-remote">
        <title>Remote debugging</title>
        <para>
            Debugging on a single machine is not always practical, because the
            target application may run full-screen, or take over the keyboard or
            mouse.
        </para>
        <para>
            Several options exist to use <command>gldb-gui</command> on a
            separate machine to the target application. However,
            <emphasis>all</emphasis> of them require trust between the two
            machines involved as the debugging protocol is not error-checked
            and so it would be easy for either a rogue target to attack
            <command>gldb-gui</command> or vice versa.
        </para>

        <para>
            Regardless of the method used, the X11 display running the
            debugger must in some respects be at least as capable as the
            display running the target application. Specifically, any
            texture that you view is loaded into an equivalent texture in
            the debugger, and so the texture target and dimensions must be
            supported there.
        </para>

        <refsect2 id="gldb-gui-MAN-remote-x11">
            <title>Remote X11, target on local display</title>
            <para>
                The easiest and most robust option is to rely on the networking
                in the X Windowing System. From the machine containing the
                target, start <command>gldb-gui</command> with a suitable
                <envar>DISPLAY</envar> to place the GUI on a remote machine.
                Then go to
                <menuchoice>
                    <guimenu>Options</guimenu>
                    <guimenuitem>Target</guimenuitem>
                </menuchoice> and set the display to the local machine
                (usually :0.0).
            </para>
            <para>
                Although X11 can directly connect to a remote display over the
                network, this is not an encrypted connection and may not be
                secure. SSH has an X-forwarding option (<option>-x</option>),
                but with the default setting it does not forward GLX and so it
                will not work if you have compiled gldb-gui with OpenGL
                support. However, the <option>-Y</option> forwards the
                connection as <firstterm>trusted</firstterm>, and in this mode
                GLX is supported.  Please see &mp-security; to understand the
                security implications of this before you proceed.
            </para>
        </refsect2>

        <refsect2 id="gldb-gui-MAN-remote-x11-rev">
            <title>Remote X11, target on remote display</title>
            <para>
                The same setup as above may be used in reverse: the target
                runs on a remote display, while <command>gldb-gui</command>
                runs on the local display.  The disadvantage of this is that
                the application is now using indirect rendering, which may
                affect its performance as well as its behaviour.
            </para>
        </refsect2>

        <refsect2 id="gldb-gui-MAN-remote-ssh">
            <title>SSH-tunnelled debugger protocol</title>
            <para>
                This scenario is highly experimental and extremely fragile.
                The debugger and target execute on separate machines, and
                communicate over SSH rather than through a local pipe. Because
                the debugger protocol was not designed for networking, this
                currently places severe restrictions on the machines used:
            </para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem><para>They must use the same byte representations for
                        types. In particular, they must have the same endianness,
                        and it may be necessary for them to have the same word size.
                </para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>They must the same internal enumeration of types.
                        Generally this is only guaranteed if they are the same
                        version of &bugle;, compiled with the same compiler and
                        the same OpenGL headers. In some cases it may be
                        sufficient to copy <filename>src/data/gl.tu</filename>
                        from one build to another and re-build (but do not
                        <emphasis>not</emphasis> run <command>make
                            clean</command>, as this will cause the copied
                        file to be regenerated).
                </para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>The <guilabel>Backtrace</guilabel> tab and the
                        <guimenuitem>Attach GDB</guimenuitem> action will not
                        work.
                </para></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>
                To use this mode, go to 
                <menuchoice>
                    <guimenu>Options</guimenu>
                    <guimenuitem>Target</guimenuitem>
                </menuchoice>
                and change the mode to <guilabel>Remote via SSH</guilabel>. In
                the remote host, put the hostname as it will be passed to
                &mp-ssh; (it can also contain a username). You must also
                configure <application>ssh</application> to log into the
                machine without prompting for a password.
            </para>
        </refsect2>
    </refsect1>

    &author;

    <refsect1>
        <title>See also</title>
        <para>&mp-bugle;, &mp-ssh;, &mp-security;</para>
    </refsect1>
</refentry>
