<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % myentities SYSTEM "bugle.ent" >
%myentities;
]>
<chapter id="install">
    <title>Installing Bugle</title>
    <sect1 id="install-requirements">
        <title>Requirements</title>
        <para>
            Bugle is intended to work on any POSIX-compliant operating system
            that use the X Windowing System, dynamic linking, and
            <envar>LD_PRELOAD</envar> for library interposition. If it fails
            to work on such an operating system, please let me know (I only
            use it on GNU/Linux). Windows and Mac OSX are not currently
            supported as they are not based on X.
        </para>
        <para>
            The following packages are required to compile Bugle:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para>
                    GCC, at least version 3.2, and <emphasis>not</emphasis>
                    4.0 (see the <link linkend="faq-gcc-version">FAQ</link>
                    for an explanation of why).
            </para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>
                    A C++ compiler (generally <application>g++</application>)
            </para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>OpenGL header files, including a recent version of <ulink
                        url="http://www.opengl.org/registry/api/glext.h">glext.h</ulink>
                    (older versions should work, but it will be difficult to
                    debug any code that uses newer features).
            </para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>
                    GLEW: 1.4.0 has been tested, but older versions may work
            </para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Perl 5</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>
            The following packages are not required, but if present, will
            enable extra functionality:
        </para>
        <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><ulink url="http://cnswww.cns.cwru.edu/php/chet/readline/rltop.html">readline</ulink></term>
                <listitem><para>
                        This will enable line editing in the console debugger.
                        The GUI debugger is the preferred method of debugging.
                </para></listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><ulink url="http://www.gtk.org/">GTK+</ulink></term>
                <listitem><para>
                        This is needed for the GUI debugger.
                </para></listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><ulink url="http://gtkglext.sourceforge.net/">gtkglext</ulink></term>
                <listitem><para>
                        This is needed for the texture and framebuffer viewers
                        in the GUI debugger.
                </para></listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><ulink url="http://ffmpeg.org/">FFmpeg</ulink></term>
                <listitem><para>
                        If FFmpeg is available, the included <systemitem
                            class="library">libavcodec</systemitem> is used
                        for video capture.
                </para></listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="install-configure">
        <title>Configuring</title>
        <para>
            Bugle uses the standard <command>configure</command> command for
            compile-time configuration. Generic instructions may be found in
            <filename>INSTALL</filename> in the root of the source directory.
            In general, <command>configure</command> will auto-detect optional
            packages and use them only if present, but you can also prevent it
            from depending on certain packages with the following flags:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para><option>--without-lavc</option></para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><option>--without-readline</option></para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><option>--without-gtk</option></para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><option>--without-gtkglext</option></para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>
            Bugle does not use threads itself, but applications that it
            debugs might, and bugle needs to use appropriate locking and
            thread-local storage libraries. The correct option should be
            auto-detected, but you can force it with
            <option>--with-threads</option>=<replaceable>model</replaceable>.
            Valid models are <literal>pthreads</literal> and
            <literal>single</literal> (i.e., no threads).
        </para>
        <para>
            Finally, bugle intercepts events from X11. While there are no
            known cases of this causing problems, it is difficult to make
            the interception completely transparent, and so the
            <option>--disable-xevent</option> option is
            available to disable it at compile time.
        </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="install-compile">
        <title>Compiling and installing</title>
        <para>
            Compilation is as simple as running <userinput>make</userinput>.
            Before installing, you should remove any previous installation of
            bugle to avoid leaving old versions of files around. If you do not
            have your original installation tree to run <userinput>make
                uninstall</userinput>, you should at least remove the files in
            <filename><replaceable>/usr/local/lib/</replaceable>bugle</filename>
            and
            <filename><replaceable>/usr/local/lib/</replaceable>libbugle*</filename>.
            To install the new version, run <userinput>make
                install</userinput> as <systemitem
                class="username">root</systemitem>.
        </para>
        <para>
            Next, you need to install some files for the user that will run
            bugle. Create a directory <filename
                class="directory">$HOME/.bugle</filename>, and copy
            <filename>doc/examples/filters</filename> and
            <filename>doc/examples/statistics</filename> into it.
        </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="install-windows">
        <title>Compiling on Windows</title>
        <para>
            Installing from source on Windows is supported, but it is
            significantly trickier than on
            UNIX-like systems, and currently only recommended for experts.
            The intended target is <ulink
                url="http://www.mingw.org">MinGW</ulink>; you can try using
            Cygwin as well, but it is not tested.
        </para>
        <para>
            Apart from the core of MinGW, you will need to install MSYS, Perl,
            regex (user-contributed version), and msysDTK. If you install GTK+
            and GtkGLExt,
            you need to ensure that <command>pkg-config</command> knows
            where to find them (setting <envar>PKG_CONFIG_PATH</envar>
            appropriately). If you install GLEW, you need to ensure that the
            compiler and linker can find it (setting <envar>CPATH</envar> and
            <envar>LIBRARY_PATH</envar> appropriately).
        </para>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
